[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello everyone welcome to this episode
of software engineering radio
this is your host kanchan shrinky and
today i'm really happy to welcome
drooper berthicker
to our podcast we're going to talk about
embedding real-time analytics
in applications druva is c2n co-founder
at
rockset he was the founding engineer of
the rocksdb data store at facebook
earlier at yahoo he was also one of the
founding engineers of the hadoop
distributor file system druba has also
been a contributor to the open source
apache edge-based project
druba previously held various roles at
veritas software
founded an e-commerce startup called
oneriscip.com
and contributed to the andrew file
system at ibm
transact labs you have quite an
impressive resumethruba
so happy to have you here and really
looking forward to today's conversation
is there anything you'd like to add to
your bio no thank you
kanchan thanks for inviting me really
appreciate your invitation here
i'm very excited to be talking to you
about real-time analytics
let's let's get started yeah so
before we jump into it i do want to
point out that we have done a few
related
episodes in the past and there are about
five or six episodes we'll have a link
to those in our show notes
any include any references that we
discovered during our conversation as
well rubra
so why don't we start with a very basic
question
what is real-time analytics yeah that's
a great question
i have been asked this question many
times and
sometimes it's difficult to explain as a
definition but what i can try is
to give you examples or define what is
real-time analytics
so real-time analytics is typically a
way
for somebody to look at very fresh data
and make decisions based on this data
take for example you are trying to make
a prediction or you are trying to
understand relationships between
different
events happening in your system and you
want to do it in real time in the sense
you want to do this
decision making as soon as the data gets
produced
so this is real-time analytics it has
two characteristics usually
it's about the freshness of data and how
quickly can you make decisions based on
this data
sometimes people also talk about real
real-time analytics
as analytics that are very customer
focused
because if you try to make decisions
based on behalf of a customer
or a user these are people who are
online who are waiting for
the results to appear so the need the
queries need to be really fast for these
kinds of analytical applications
a very simple example for real-time
analytics could be
take for example google maps take for
example right you were driving down the
highway and there's an accident
now your app in this case the google
maps app
have to show you an alternate route and
that has to happen
in real time it cannot be based on
traffic data that was created
like 10 minutes ago right so this is a
very simple example of how
real-time analytics are kind of built
into some of these back-end applications
that are becoming more and more
prevalent these days
the two things are of course someone's
waiting for the data they've asked a
question they want a response right away
but also that the decision the response
has to be
based on really fresh data and you
provide a great use case for that
yeah the freshness of data is super
important for real-time analytics
there are many other systems that are in
the analytical domain that
is about making decisions but a lot of
those applications
make decisions based on old data for
real-time analytics
the freshness of data is super important
for for these kind of applications
so you brought up other applications so
this is a good time maybe you can
contrast with how
traditionally olap and olap operations
are understood
so if i contrast with traditional
analytics
you brought up this term called all app
and say oltp right so take for example
olap
people refer to all app as online kind
of analytical
processing so they're online in nature
but again the data
is usually not as fresh as people would
like it to be
most of the applications that are out
there
they build cubes for example or they
build pre-aggregations they
already try to kind of summarize the
data
in in more coarse-grained formats so
that queries are fast on this data
which basically means that they curate
the data they clean the data
to put it in a variable form and after
that when they serve the queries the
data is not changing in nature
so by definition most of these all app
systems
are there where you take a bunch of data
you
process it and then you start to use it
to make decisions
so by definition it's not real time
because by the time you
took this data and made it variable you
are doing some kind of a patch
processing system
this is how traditional analytics happen
these all app applications they need
to typically scan through a lot of data
and they make
something called cubes cube is like more
like a bucketization
software where you say pre-aggregated
correct exactly they pre-aggregate in
using nine
or n different dimensions and now
because they're pre-aggregated queries
are fast
but the challenge again is that because
it's pre-aggregated it doesn't mean that
it has taken any of your fresh data into
account
and that's how traditional analytics
works and the processing takes time as
you mentioned
processing takes time making the cubes
take time
the cubes don't change once you make a
cube let's say you make a cube
every day for 10 minute cubes right now
you can't really
backfill data into this 10 minute cubes
that you already made
so it makes your analytics not real time
in nature in general
the only way to change this model to
make it more real time
is to be able to build a lot more
real-time indexes or
lots of pointers into this data so you
can update things in place
so that you can make it more real-time
in the future people have built
indexes on this data rather than cubes
building an index is a great way to kind
of make data real time
rather than building a cube because
indexes can be updated
as and when new data comes in but yeah i
mean there is a
big difference between how all app
traditional queries happen
and how real-time analytics typically
occur in real life
is there any relation to the amount of
data is there you know
where does big data come in big data is
kind of a very
ambiguous term these days right in 2005
i think big data revolution kind of
started or 2006 around that time
but what has happened right now is that
almost all data sets are big data by
definition
which basically means that if there's a
solution or if you have a system that
deals
only with small data sets that is
usually something that is not
interesting to most people
so now i think the other things that i
can add to
your question is that big data itself
has kind of
two or three different dimensions one is
the velocity of data which means that
how fast is this data coming
one is the size of the data which means
that how big is this data set
and the third one is what is the variety
of data like how much complex is this
data is it all one format or is it five
different formats coming in
so for real-time analytics i think it's
super important
to be able to be able to process
different data formats
it's super important to be able to deal
with a high velocity of data
so let's say you might want to pin me
down but i would say that maybe
somewhere between
a few megabytes per second to a few
gigabytes per second could be the
velocity of data that's coming in
this is new data produced by events
right this is your streaming data set
that you are capturing
by your application and you want to look
at all this data to make decisions
so this is the challenge for real-time
analytics i keep going back to my
thinking is that real-time analytics is
hard
because of these reasons three things to
write for me you know besides being
fresh
it is typical that all the data today
will be of high velocity changing
and different variety a large number of
data sources
and then you set streaming so what is
streaming analytics
and how does that contrast with
real-time analytics
yeah so streaming analytics and
real-time
analytics are complementary in nature i
think
so when we talk about streaming
analytics we usually refer to the fact
that analytical processing is occurring
when data is streaming into the system
i said about let's say high velocity of
data when all the data is coming into
the system
there's a at that time itself you could
afford to do some processing
when new data arrives it triggers a set
of actions that generate
insights from the data this is streaming
analytics because it's happening as part
of the stream
it's also sometimes called as right time
analytics where data where
analytics happen when data arrives into
the system
these insights once new data comes into
the system you can generate
insights and those insights can trigger
more downstream analytical processing
this is all called streaming analytics
it's like a data waterfall
like like waterfall water falling from a
higher
level to a lower level at every level
when
data is flowing downstream it's
processing some analytical
decision making this is all streaming
analytics
on the other hand real-time analytics
typically use a combination of both
right time analytics as well as read
time analytics so
you could have some streaming analytics
which is building some
right time aggregations but if you're
talking about just
real time analytics it also needs
a lot of variability in the queries a
lot of complex
power in your queries itself because
your queries could be different from
point to point
if my application is making a query to
the database my query could be
completely different from another person
making a query to the same
back-end source so essentially real-time
analytics uses a combination of
streaming analytics
as well as query time analytics to
provide the real timeliness of your
application
so that kind of two different
complementary things
if you have streaming analytics it
doesn't need to be real-time
but if you have real-time analytics it's
usually the case that you need
some form of streaming analytics and
some form of query analytics built into
the system
so that you can respond to fresh data
quickly at high volume and at large
scale
so they're complementary to one another
i would say okay got it so streaming is
assumed in a sense and over that you
have return analytics
so there's still work going on there's
still processing going on
so how real time is this or is this near
real time so is it minutes seconds
can you talk about that so again i think
when you talk about real-time analytics
we talk about freshness of data
and i think your question is that how
fresh is this data is it one second
freshness or is it one day freshness so
that's
an answer that depends on the
application itself but in general
when the industry talks about real-time
analytics they're mostly talking about
a data latency of say a few seconds to a
few minutes
so this is why okay so let me backtrack
and explain the difference between data
latency and query related
data latency measures how real time is
your data
it is the latency from when the data was
produced to the time when
it is available to make decisions right
it's available in your query engine
that's the data latency and query
latency is when you issue a query
how long does it take for the query to
come back with results from your backend
system
so for real-time analytics the data
latencies usually are a few
seconds to maybe maybe a minute or two
let me give you an example let's say you
are like in a food delivery
use case right you have an enterprise
that's delivering food from
picking up food from restaurants and
delivering it at homes
now there may be let's say the entire
distance of
our entire delivery cycle is let's say
15 minutes right
for a back-end system that can react to
changes in delivery like
a delivery person is breaking down or
the food is not ready or available
so there less than a minute is your
should be your data latency because you
need to react
because your entire cycle is just 15
minutes right so from pickup to delivery
so there the data latency could be
really small that you need for real-time
analytics
but on the other hand if your logistics
system is delivering
luggages or goods from one place to
another from the east coast to the west
coast you might have only one train that
comes every day
so there your data latency could be
maybe
minutes or maybe an hour or so as well
the whole point is that
real-time analytics essentially reduces
the latency of your data
it is sometimes people also ask me these
questions about
are the systems online or offline that's
another way to look at
how real time this data latency can be
and my answer there is that real-time
analytics
mostly are online systems they're not
offline back-end batch systems
they're systems that if they don't react
quickly
then your targets or your audience
suffers an outage or suffers a
disadvantage or to suffer
bad decisions which are not optimal for
your business or it's not optimal for
the users of your system
yeah so it's kind of not very clear cut
in my mind exactly what the number is
but it's usually seconds to minutes
so you've given us a couple of examples
of
use cases and in that there was already
an action that had to be taken your
google use case for maps for people to
read out so essentially the
the goal is for people to perform an
action right not just
being able to get the information but be
able to perform the action in which case
of course the user performing the action
but there are other cases where i guess
there has to be an automated action
also required would you be able to
provide any such use case
most of the real-time analytics systems
that we see
in real life they are actually automated
in nature
i took the google maps example just to
give you give it like a human color
but actually the decision-making process
is very much automatic for most
other systems so take for example
let's say we talk about like say
construction logistics delivery company
right
there's an enterprise which is in the
business of
producing cement and delivering it to
construction places places where big
buildings are being constructed
so you'd be actually amazed that there's
a strict
latency between when the cement is mixed
and when it needs to be put
on the building otherwise it goes waste
so now what happens is that there is a
complex
process where at the construction site
there are a lot of sensors which is
figuring out how how well is my
hydraulic lift working how fast is it
able to do its work how many steel pipes
have i installed till now because based
on all those sensors
is when the cement needs to be mixed in
a far away place
and then the cement is loaded into
trucks and delivered to this
construction site now this is all
could be automatic this is a very
real-time analytic situation
where you are getting sensors from many
different objects in a construction site
that's being fed into a back-end system
and then
based on irregularities or anomalies of
this process
the cement needs to be mixed at a
different time and then loaded into
trucks and delivered here
so this is very automatic process
there's no humans involved i mean it's
all
software and then here the data latency
is super important for these kind of
users because
if they miss deadlines then the cmail
goes waste
the driver who drives the truck c band
and it
gets into the construction site finds
out that all these three hours of
driving has gone waste because now the
cement cannot be used at the right place
the right time
so there are lots of industries where
the cost of a non-optimized
algorithm to deliver their products is
super
impactful for their products and their
business and
this is where real-time analytics is
really useful for these kind of use
cases
similarly i think you might have seen
also like flight trackers or
flight paths that are being taken by
airlines
there also a lot of it is real-time
analytics because
constantly the machines on the ground
are actually
telling the planes exactly how to what
route exactly do you take
i mean there is a direction that's said
in the beginning but there are
so many small changes being made in the
route as and when the system and the
plane is running
and these are all automatic systems
there are not people making decisions
from minute to minute or second to
second these are all software making
decisions
based on fresh data thank you for those
two examples they certainly make a lot
of sense to me
and in both cases you know it was clear
to see
the fact that there is a lot of data
this is big data
the velocity is changing the sensors are
constantly generating data
and certainly the variety them probably
many many different kinds of sensors
so i think it matched all the metrics
that you asked us to look out for
for real-time analytics and clearly for
these it's
the use case seems obvious if you don't
do this if your flight path is
not correctly computed it could have
accidents in the other
case the cement could go waste as well
so that's clear but
it may not always be the case that you
need to have decisions right away so i'm
sure it's based on the use case
so how do people come to a decision that
they need real-time analytics because
i'm sure there are costs
associated with this there must be some
cons because otherwise you know why
wouldn't you do this
all the time maybe let's start by
talking about the costs involved
and then we can see in what what are the
things you would ask people to look out
for to know that yes they do need
real-time
analytics there is definitely a cost to
real-time analytics right so
real-time analytics is a hard problem to
solve
that's why most current use cases that
people use
they use data analytics there's they
said that okay i'm going to live with
daily analytics where my data is one
hour old or
one day old because i can't i don't have
the resources to be able to do real-time
analytics that's how the state of
affairs were in the software industry
in the last decade or so but things are
changing now but coming back to your
cost
the question of cost is super important
so the cost of real-time analytics is
falling actually day by day not because
some new invention has happened but
because
more and more people find that this is
an important problem to solve so there
are new techniques that are being
developed
so the biggest cost of real-time
analytics
is that first you have to plan for all
types of data this is not easy so
in traditional ways people will set up
five different systems to
deal with five different data sets and
then they have to manage all these data
sets
all these five different systems by
themselves they might have a relational
database they might have some
document database they might have some
other kind of backend systems to deal
with
this variety of data so that's a big
cost to
in general for people the other is
essentially
operational overhead of real-time
analytics the operational overhead
of of reacting like let's say you have a
highest
volume of data coming in and suddenly
something is not working now
all the traffic needs to be rerouted
through a different channel so that you
don't lose any of that data
you see what i'm saying so real-time
analytics is not just about
getting data and processing but it's
about keeping all these big pipes
up all the time 24 by 7 so that you
never lose some pieces of data otherwise
your system is going to
be a problem so there are big costs
involved in it
but i can also explain how some of the
newer technologies are helping people to
surmount some of these challenges
regarding cost
take for example there are lots of
public clouds that people are
leveraging to kind of deploy these data
systems
so that's one way where there's a lot of
automatic processes that help you do
fault recovery right like if your
machine goes down there are automatic
ways to
spin up new machines or new hardware and
not have to lose any of the data
that's coming in at high volume
similarly
again i can go into some more depth
about
how systems have evolved over from batch
to real time
and how some software changes have
happened
to be able to manage all these costs the
costs essentially have come down
drastically over the last maybe year or
so now or maybe last two three years
but it's it's something that people
should definitely think about
because the cost is not just about the
streaming data but also the high volume
of queries that you need
because most of these real-time
analytics are
used by other pieces of software so they
need to make queries
at sometimes at high volume and high qps
that's definitely one cost and the last
part of the cost is about
matching demand so it's likely that
the workload of your system needs to go
high during the day time and then maybe
there's no work
for it in the night time like take for
example my semen construction
company most of the time in the night
there is not much work going on in this
in this business because the physical
workers are not constructing the
buildings
that much so your system has to manage
cost by being able to spin down unused
resources
when not in use and then spin them up
back again when
daytime starts again this has to be
automatic this is what i mean by there
are lots of
traditional costs but a lot of the newer
systems are out there
they try to avoid these costs by
building software to be more intelligent
so my takeaway was really that
maintaining the data systems themselves
then absorbing the operational overhead
of making sure that the system is
operating all the time matching demand
tuning it so that you are able to react
when you do need to react
and what do you do when you don't need
to react are you ensuring that
your systems are well utilized for some
other purpose maybe at that time
and public clouds have certainly helped
in this area
that was my takeaway from this so thank
you this is a good introduction to
you know what is real-time systems some
basic use cases
and we also talked about the costs of it
so taking a step back
let's talk about batch because i assume
that's where people started
contrasting batch with term analytics a
little bit more
what did people do earlier what were the
typical components used for
batch mode analytics has always been
batch
for the last maybe 30 or 40 years now
since
people invented computers to store data
and do analytical processing on it
but if you look at only at say big data
systems
most of big data started around in 2005
or 2006
or 2000 somewhere around middle of that
decade
and it all started with a paper from
google which talked about the google
file system they said that oh
google produced a research paper saying
that this is how large data sets can be
stored
in disk systems right and using the
paper there was a project that got built
in open source it was called apache
hadoop
project i was part of the project and
this is a system that essentially let
you store a lot of
large data sets but the focus
always has been or at that time was
how can you store terabytes terabytes
and petabytes of data into this system
the focus wasn't how quickly can you
make decisions you see the so the design
goal of these systems were very
different
in the last decade the last decade the
challenge was
how can i store petabytes of data cost
effectively and
cheaply and not have to drain all my
pockets
so this is where hadoop became very
popular it was one of the first systems
that you can store a lot of data
you can make queries you there is
something called hadoop mapreduce which
again is a very scan based system
because these are all batch systems the
focus was
queries that can do full scans of your
data
and produce results and reports the
focus was not on
leveraging your most recent data set the
focus was not on low latency queries
the focus was entirely on how can i
store
petabytes of data and then i can make
once gigantic scan of this data and give
me results that i am looking for
so that is how it all started in the
beginning
but then another kind of evolution that
happened is that
sql systems started to take a little bit
of hold in this
in the beginning hadoop or any of these
big data systems
were very much key value stores or like
some custom apis but then people
saw that using sql is a great way to
leverage the data in these systems
because
sql is a way that's easily
understandable and
many developers can adopt it very
quickly you can express
very complex computations using very
simple
sql statements so it's the is the
developer doesn't have to think about
a lot of complexity it just specifies
that hey this is what i want to do with
these two data sets i want to join this
large data set with this data set and
then
i want to do some aggregations and it
supported the software to
execute all those commands so the
developer or the application developer
really liked to use sql or the bi
analysts
so sql started to take hold on these
systems
and now more and more big data systems
or
any data systems i feel like sql has
become kind of
the lingua franca of all these
applications not because
sql is some it's a magic language it's
just because it's a
very versatile language it allows you to
do
all kinds of operations with the data in
a very declarative way you don't have to
write a program
or or a functional program to specify
the steps you just tell the system that
i want to do these things
you figure out how to do it best and
give me the results so this is why sql
has become so popular on some of these
big data systems but it's a
it's an evolution i feel as far as
traditional data systems are concerned
they're very much
batch systems and full scan systems and
this is why real-time analytics wasn't
really possible on those kind of systems
they were very batch oriented and batch
oriented means that
you cannot take fresh data into account
because you create a batch
of data to be processed and then you
keep processing it for the next
hour or the next day so is hdfs no
longer part of the ecosystem for
building real-time analytics
yeah that's a good question so i was the
project leader of the hadoop file system
back in the days
when it was a very cutting-edge software
project i feel like hadoop
has kind of lost this charm in the last
maybe
two three years back in the days it was
a very powerful system
but now what has happened is that people
have started to move to the cloud
and the cloud means like said amazon aws
cloud or google cloud or azure or some
other cloud systems
and there these cloud vendors already
have an hdfs
equivalent system that is pre-installed
for you
like in amazon it's called s3 so you can
have an object store that
scales infinitely so there is no
advantage or there is no
differentiator as an enterprise who is
using hadoop to be able to say hey i run
my own hadoop because
the cloud vendors run it for you so hdfs
i think is losing its charm
similarly mapreduce which is very much a
batch system
is not what people are looking for these
days because again
mostly people are thinking about
real-time analytics not batch analytics
so it's changing also if you use hadoop
you still look at things in a very
old-fashioned way you have to look at
capacity planning
your hadoop cluster you would have to
look at how much cpu you use how much
storage you combine together in the hdfs
cluster
whereas if you use some of these cloud
vendors solutions
they are actually display as you as you
use service you don't have to capacity
plan any of these things
you don't have to think in advance how
much data you're going to use the next
day or next month
so people have more or less migrated to
a lot of
cloud storage systems that are out there
but hdfs
or hadoop is still used by some
enterprises i'll give you one or two
examples without naming the people
because i work closely with these
enterprises
there is this company which is which
deals with buying and selling used cars
they have a service that allows users to
see what others paid for
similar cars in their neighborhood or in
the local area
and published this to the dealers of the
cars they store all these data on an
on-prem
hadoop file system right and they use
something called hbase which is a
database
and a key value store built on top of
hadoop but again
this is not a real-time system this is
the difference of those systems
like they can look at used car prices
of yesterday and earlier but not like
the latest ones
like if somebody is making any changes
today they don't get reflected for 24
hours
similarly there are some big financial
firms
that continue to use hadoop first of all
they have
far more restrictions and regulations
but they do store things like
mortgage deeds on loan repayment history
these kind of things on hadoop and they
run the risk assessment and analysis on
hadoop file system and these risk
numbers that don't really change from
like minute to minute or
hour to hour so it's okay for them to
not have this real time
concept for these kind of use cases on
the hadoop back end
okay so the point is that the use case
it was built for
at that time was quite different and a
change is certainly needed
so moving on to that you know like
what's new what have you been working on
would like to focus on that
i read a little bit about rock set and i
came across the term aggregate relief
tailor
architecture so i do want to ask you
about that
but before that what is lambda and what
are
shortcomings why did you have to create
something brand new
so for people who are in the data
landscape or who
people who deal with data systems
software systems
i think the lambda architecture has
become very popular in the last few
years
so what the lambda architecture is is
that
it says that there is a batch pipeline
to
load data into your system and then
there is also a streaming pipeline into
which
you load data into your system so the
lambda architecture says that there are
two
pipelines to load data into your system
you cannot get rid of any of these
because you need real timeliness it's
great to have these two
pipelines built into your system the
lambda architecture the focus of it is
that how can we get
good efficiency and good throughput of
your system
that's the design goal of the lambda
architecture so which means that you
have
let's say 100 terabytes of data which
means your bulk
processing pipeline but then you also
have say one gigabyte of data per second
coming in which means that there is a
streaming component to it
and the lambda architecture very clearly
says that this is how you should build a
system
so that your system is optimized and
you get the best value for your money
compared to the amount of data
that is coming into your system but you
realize that
it is not really talking about real time
analytics it's all talking about
efficiency and throughput of your system
now
based on our discussion i hope it's
getting clear
in our in our minds that real-time
analytics is about efficiency but the
real
focus is ability to react very quickly
to changes in your events so it seems
similar to
your answer to the earlier question on
the difference between what is streaming
analytics and what is real-time
analytics
so beyond just loading the system
which seems to be the focus of the
lambda architecture you're saying
there's to be
more optimizations needed for the
reading correct
absolutely so lambda doesn't tell you
much about how fast can your queries be
how are your query changing from minute
to minute what is the query volume
of your workload those are not part of
the design
of the lambda architecture okay so then
let's jump into the specific technical
accomplishments
with the aggregator leaf tiller
architecture we at rock said we use the
aggregator leaf tailor architecture
in short we call it the alt so the alt
architecture
by itself is not something that suddenly
came out of the blue because of a
lightning bolt from the sky right
it is inspired by many of the systems we
built
when i was at facebook some of the
back-end systems
i'll give an example of where you might
be already using
alt architecture system if you use
facebook
you load the facebook app and then you
see the facebook
feed right the data feed which is about
comments
posts likes from your friends so that's
a data feed that's coming in at actually
very
high volume for because all your friends
are posting things or liking pictures
and it's an analytic system that
facebook news feed because it doesn't
show you everything
it does a combination of your best
friends that is tries to apply
some logic between a ranking between all
the feeds that are
that can possibly show in your system
right and it does relevance matching
sorting and then shows you the feed
from the facebook app so this is a real
time
feed which is focused on reducing data
latency you don't want to see posts from
your comments
from your friends which was posted
yesterday right you want to see them
right
when your friend posted the comment so
this back end was built using an alt
architecture
or lt-like architecture so what happens
is that
the beauty of the alt architecture is
that it is focused
on serving low latency queries on large
datasets
it has to be efficient and optimized and
throughput optimized just like lambda
but it has an additional constraint that
your queries
have to be fast and you should be able
to support a large volume of queries
if needed so this is the difference from
the use case perspective this is the
difference of an
alt architecture now if i double click
on it
and i peel off one more layer of the
onion
the technical differentiator of the lt
architecture is that
it has three components it has the
aggregators leaf
and the tailor so the tailor
is the component who is basically
involved in writing to the system so
when you're sending data into the system
is the tailors who is actually indexing
this data
or creating it in a format that is
queryable
that's where a lot of work is happening
on the tailors
and then the taylor sends it to the
leaves and the leaves
are the components that store this data
persistently so you don't lose it
so this is kind of your storage system
the leads
and then the aggregators are part of the
query system so when queries come in
the aggregators of the components that
fetch data from the leaves and do
whatever processing your sql query might
be
telling you to do and then give you
results so there are three
separate stages in the alt architecture
and the reason why this is important is
because this is a disaggregated
architecture
perfectly built for cloud systems this
did not appeal much when you have an
on-prem system where your hardware is
fixed
the reason it's a disaggregated
architecture is that it's very
cloud friendly and i can explain again
why so what happens is that
if there's a high volume if your right
rate to your
system increases then you spin up more
and more tailors
you don't have to touch the leaves and
aggregators because
it's just more data is coming in but the
amount of data that you have in your
system is constant or the queries are
not increasing in
nature so you just need to scale up the
tailor similarly when there is no data
you spin down the tailors and you don't
have any extra cost for the tailing
component right
similarly if your data set increases day
over day and month over month
then you need to add more and more
leaves but if your data set is
decreasing because
of whatever reason then you can keep
shrinking the number of storage nodes
and the leaves in this system
and the aggregators these are actually
super exciting because
when more queries come you spin up more
aggregators and you serve them at the
same low latency that
your real-time system needs but then
when there's no more load and
people are sleeping or whatever in the
nighttime or maybe it's not christmas
day so
something else or less load you can spin
down all your
aggregators and you have no cost for
spinning up
so basically the disaggregated
architecture of alt is cloud friendly
and it can
give you the lowest cost compared to an
on-prem system
where you have to provision everything
for peak capacity this ties into your
other assist other question you asked me
saying how can you reduce cost
for real-time analytics so alt
architecture is a great way to reduce
cost as well because it's disaggregated
in nature
could you contrast it with apache druid
flink and kudu
you know from my impression they have
been used for similar use cases
so a great question from an architecture
perspective there are different systems
so like i said the aggregator leaf
tailor architecture
because the three parts of the system
so what has happened is that the three
things that are disaggregated
in this architecture is the cpu that you
need to
write data to the system right and then
the second thing is the amount of
storage in your system
and then the cpu that you need to solve
queries from your system
there are three different things in this
architecture whereas take for example if
you look at apache kudu or druid
there is no clear separation between the
compute that you need to write data into
the system
versus the compute you need to query
there are shared set of compute servers
so now what will happen is that i mean
that works fine for many use cases but
the
challenge for that architecture is that
if suddenly you have the high right
volume
let's say suddenly some software started
to send lot
100 times more data than it was doing
last hour
now your queries will suffer because
it's sharing the same amount of cpu
or the same set of compute nodes that
are used for
writing the data as well as squaring the
data they're not segregated in nature
so it's because it is shared in nature
which is why
similarly if suddenly there is a high
number of queries coming into
an existing system let's say grid for
example
your new data might get delayed because
now it's not as fresh anymore because
all the compute is being used to solve
all the queries in your system
so this is one big difference from the
architecture perspective
now you also mentioned about flink so
flink is very much a streaming system
which basically means again the
difference between streaming analytics
and real-time analytics
so take for example in alt architecture
you could actually do use flink as well
as part of the tailors you could think
about flink as if
the tailors are made of flink nodes
where things are happening when data is
coming into the system
but then you actually store it in the
leaves where the
actual data storage is and then
aggregators could still be there to
query all the data that your
flink has outputted to the leads
so flink more is like a streaming system
where you can process data as and when
it's coming in
and after you are done processing you
can park it in the leads and then the
queries can come in through the
aggregator so they're kind of
complementary to one another
flink also could be similar to say sparx
streaming uh use cases where you can use
it more like an etl tool
where it's a set of transformations that
you can do using flink and then you can
park it
in an alt architecture system and then
you can start queries using the leaves
and aggregators so yeah i think i have
seen people who kind of use that
in that the alt architecture as well as
flink together in one system
the message that i keep getting is the
fact that a lot of these systems
were optimized for the storage and
what you're now focusing on is how to
make the query
better with real time indexing and how
to scale these
three components separately so that this
cloud native
absolutely so the focus for the alt
architecture is how can you serve a lot
of queries
efficiently how can you make the queries
low latency and how can you make sure
that
you use only the minimum amount of
hardware needed to serve these queries
so there are three things to make these
queries efficient you also mentioned
about indexing
so indexing is super useful for us to be
able to
serve queries in low latency i mean
indexing is
is a time tested way of reducing query
latencies i mean if you look at
mysql database or the database that was
produced
even anything else in formix whatever
else was there 40 years back they all
had
this thing called indexing it just that
nobody had actually used indexing on
large data sets before
so most of the indexing was for small
like
very relational kind of transactional
databases
people never actually used indexing for
analytical applications what now people
are realizing is that
to serve low latency queries on large
data sets you need to index this data
indexing is the way to reduce latency of
queries
so the aggregator leaf tailor
architecture lets you do this because
there is
cost of indexing at the time when data
comes in which is the tailors
and then there is a cost for the queries
to be able to use the index
as part of the queries which is done by
the aggregator so yes the lt
architecture definitely helps the
indexing part of things
yeah on the indexing i did read the term
converged
indexing so can you explain what's that
there are two or three different types
of indexing that people
are used to in the software industry are
things like
a columnar index columnar index is an
index where
all the columns of of your records are
stored together
let's say you have a table with three
fields right name
and age and salary let's say there are
three columns in your
in your database now if you keep all the
salaries in one place
separately from the other two fields if
somebody says
hey give me the average salary of a
person
i can just scan through all the salary
fields of
all the billions of records in my
database and give you the average it's
very fast
so columnar storage or columnar index is
a traditional way to make
scan type of queries fast that's one
type of
index that people are used to then the
other type of
index people are used to are something
called inverted index
so inverted index is what is essentially
used by open source software like
leucine and elasticsearch
they are used essentially to give you
very low latency on
point queries like suppose you have a
query to this table saying that
find me the person whose salary is
exactly one thousand dollars
right so now that probably like three
percent in your
billion or million people database if
you build an inverted index those
queries will come back really fast it
doesn't have to stand the entire table
to figure this out this is the second
type of index and the third type of
index
are essentially very much like a
relational table with a primary key
in this example i gave you you have the
name and the age and the salary
you could have an index with say the
employee id
of the person so that's the fourth index
and so now
that's how traditionally relational
tables are stored with the primary key
and that's a record or a row based index
that you have which is could be
indexed by the employee id of the person
so if somebody is the person is getting
hired or
leaving the company you can use the
employee id to find its record and
update the fields in the record
right so the converged indexing is
essentially building
all these kind of indexes as one thing
in the packet
so the application doesn't have to
specify what indexes to build
the system automatically builds these
indexes
and then based on the query it tries to
use the right index for the right
purpose
so typically converge index means that
you build like an inverted index you
build a columnar index
you build a row index as one thing and
you store it and leverage
in the in your queries just to give it a
little bit more color
the row index is essentially very much
like mysql or mongodb
indexes that they build by default the
inverted index is very much like what
lucien or elasticsearch builds by
default and a columnar index is very
much like an index that is built by
say redshift or snowflake or vertica
or any other kind of analytical software
so this is the association that
the index essentially builds indexes
from all these different types of
backend systems you might be used to
and store it in one place this obviously
affect
the rate at which you're able to ingest
the data as well
so maybe talk about some of the
technical challenges there
is that what led to the separation and
trying to scale them
independently yeah in general i think
people think that building indexes is
costly
that's why most databases have a field
saying
create index on this column if your
record has 500 fields they don't want to
build
500 indexes because building indexes
in general has been a difficult
proposition for most users
but at rockstead what we do is that we
do build a converged index
for all the fields in your data because
the rockstep technology
has tried to make the cost of indexing
much lower compared to traditional
systems so it actually makes it
economically feasible to build indexes
on every field of your data
so now think about the power of the
system you don't need a dba first of all
to build an index
on whatever fields are there an index is
built on every field and so now when a
query comes in
almost all the queries are fast because
the indexes are on
every field of your data you asked me
about the challenges of building that
index
so the challenges are multi-fold but let
me tell you how the challenges
are addressed in our software one of the
challenges is that we don't use
a b tree to store these data so
typically a binary tree or b
tree is how databases store data like so
what happens is that
the b3 has something called a very
high right amplification when you are
updating data because that data gets
updated in place
whereas for building these indexes for
converged index for rockset what we do
is that
we use a log structured merge tree
instead of a b tree it's called an
allosam engine so we use an lsm engine
called
open source rocksdb so that lets us
index a large volume of data at a much
better price performance compared to a
b3 based database that people are used
to earlier
that's one and the second way we try to
address
the challenges is that rock set
conversion index is very much
built as a search engine and not like a
database
think about like google search right
when you are searching for a term
it's built for low latency but when you
are searching for
restaurants in san francisco right let's
say you're searching for that it's
actually hitting a large database
and giving you results back but the
database is optimized for latency
of query latency right your queries need
to be really fast
so rockstar is also built like this the
converged index
is basically something what what we call
it as
a document sharded database which means
that when data comes in
or a record comes in all the fields of
the record
are indexed on one machine so a record
is not split into multiple servers
even if your record is very big it has
500 fields
all the fields are going to be indexed
on one machine randomly
and then when a query comes in the query
now has to hit all the machines of your
cluster
and get results back and give you
results back to the
user so it's like kind of you just a
scatter gather kind of algorithm
to be able to fan out to all possible
machines in your cluster and get results
back from them
unlike your traditional database let's
say you were talking about grid or
something else there when a query comes
in it's going to hit
only the machines that have the data
because the data is partitioned
whereas in rockset or a converged
indexing system we scatter the data
among
all the machines in the cluster and so
when a query comes in it has to hit all
the machines in a cluster and give you
results
so the advantage of that is that it is
much more cost effective to build local
indices
on a document which is why we adopt this
approach
and building all the indexes you don't
basically need like a distributed pack
source or some other
algorithm to be able to index data large
volumes
because we have this document sharded
scatter gather way of
storing all the documents and retrieving
results
so those are two primary ways of how we
have reduced the cost of indexing on
these large streaming databases
as i hear this you know i'm thinking
this is blurring the lines for me
between oltp and olap
so do you envision this replacing
current application
workload so ltp workloads as well as
search
yeah so that's a good point so in olap
typically people just talk about
aggregations and joints which are
basically like i said
cubing and some other pre-aggregations
but when you are talking about the use
cases that
most of the real-time analytics or
facing real-time analytics are used for
they need cubing and all apps but they
also need
things like search queries they also
need
queries like ranking and relevance
matching
so these are typically not part of your
traditional
olap characterization that most people
are used to
so yeah probably we need a different
kind of
workload which is basically an olap
system but it has far more things
associated with it some people have
started to call it operational
analytics kind of thing where i think op
is the name where
online analytics operational analytical
processing where
the real timeliness of the data is super
important so it's not just about cubing
it's not just about aggregations and
joints they have to be there
but you also need searching and you also
need kind of index search indexes and
relevance ranking and pattern matching
to be able to serve all these
operational analytical queries that you
might need for real-time analytics
okay so one last question for this
section before we move on to our last
one on
embedding relative analytics there was a
note about schema-less
ingestion can you explain that yes
so schema-less ingestion falls into the
purview of real-time analytics and let
me explain why
so real-time analytics is all about
making decisions on your fresh data so
now think about
data that is coming in from five
different sources
with five different formats right one of
them is json with five fields
the other one is coming in from a
traditional relational database
the third stream is application logs
that are coming in from
say kafka or flink or something else
now if there's a way for you to take all
this data
without having to create a schema but
then make them
queryable so that people at the time of
query
can leverage the schema that is being
deciphered by the system automatically
that is called schema-less ingestion so
rockset what it does is essentially
it allows you to dump semi-structured
data from different
sources you don't have to specify a
schema at the time of writing this
database so this
basically brings out the best of nosql
database with a sql database right so
nosql databases
i feel like they became really popular
in the last decade because they could
ingest data in a free format
so this is schema-less ingestion on the
other hand
software developers don't like to
create a lot of schema themselves
because schemas keep on changing
but they need to use sql because the
sequel is a very complex and powerful
language
and prior to rockset there wasn't a way
to run
sql queries on a nosql database that's
why they're called nosql databases
so what roxa does is essentially takes
this data
it's a schemas ingest that's happening
but the system is
creating a sql schema automatically for
your application developers
that schema is based on the data that is
coming in
and because of the indexing the system
can
find out all the different pieces of
data all the different types of data
that is in the system
and it actually gives a sql interface
with a well-defined schema to
application developers
so now application developers they feel
like oh actually it's a sql system with
a great schema i can inspect the schema
i can
call described table and i can see the
schema
but nobody has to create the schema up
front so if if your new data that is
coming in has new fields they
automatically appear in the schema
this is what i mean by a schema less
ingestion with a strict schema that is
used for queries but not at the time of
writing this data
i will also include your medium post on
the alt
architecture in our show notes so
interested
listeners can go refer to that in detail
so coming to our last section which is
you know really the key focus
of our podcast today and we've been
building to that
is how to embed real-time analytics in
sas applications first of all what does
that even mean
embedding the analytics within the
application
traditionally i have seen people use
analytics
mostly to make their businesses better
how can i make my business process
better there's a lot of analytics which
tells you
that lets you do what is situations
right what if if i had done this then
how
my results have been different that's
what traditional analytics is all about
so it has nothing to do with your
the products that the company is selling
it has more to do with how the business
of that enterprise is doing now on the
other hand
in the recent time frames what we have
seen is that
a lot of analytics need to be consumed
to make the
products themselves better so i gave you
the example of the construction company
right
so their product is the ability to
deliver cement
cost effectively from one place to
another so that's their product
so how can you embed analytics into this
product
another example i'll give you online
gaming
hundreds of people are playing an online
game you need analytics
for things like creating a gaming
leaderboard the leaderboard is
who is the best player who can do these
six different things
in the last minute or so you need
real-time analytics because the
leaderboarding
query is a very complex query and you
don't want to show a leaderboard
of yesterday's data because people are
actually playing games and they want to
see the leaderboard getting refreshed as
and when
some people are winning and some people
are losing so this is what
i mean by embedding analytics into your
application
this is a newer area where where your
company's products are getting directly
impacted by analytics
it's very different from traditional
analytics which was more focused on
making businesses better
how does this change the architecture of
the application
architecture changes because you would
see
that because they're embedded in
products the volume of queries
usually vary a lot say if it was a
business
application then it would be the ceo or
the business analyst in your company who
will make a query
let's say every day or every week so the
pattern is very well defined whereas
when you build it into the
into your product i think there are
certain demands of the architecture
so the demands of the architecture is
that first of all the query latencies
have to be really
low that's one basic building block for
the architecture
and the second one is that the query
volume
also can change based on how your
product is being used by your people
take for example you're running a
fitness app on your
phone and suddenly a lot more people are
running on the road
because it's saturday so now you want to
show them
an analytical product there saying that
who are the top people who are
performing today right who's
like let's say you you also want to see
how you compared with yesterday's run
of your own schedule now you need to
show them real-time analytics on this
and the volume could change from hour to
hour very quickly
so the architecture has to be very much
focused on
low latency queries on these large data
sets
and also the volume of queries could
change from time to time or minute to
minute
so this is the two basic differences as
far as the application is concerned as
far as the data is concerned
also what happens is that the schema of
the data keeps on changing constantly
because let's say the fitness app
the application developers they will try
to capture more data from your phone
or from your device like say next week
they're going to ship
new features which is also going to
catch the temperature
of your surroundings where you're
running so now the data stream that is
coming into your data set has a new
field saying temperature
from second minute to minute now your
database
has to store this additional field with
every record
so the data variety also changes because
it's the application developer who is
controlling
what is data getting produced and what
is the data that is getting consumed
and the rate of change or application
frequently demands that your data
formats are changing or new fields are
appearing in your data that you need to
process
so you need flexibility in your
architecture that can handle
multiple data types schema-less ingest
is a great
feature for these kind of use cases and
the rate of change of your application
is basically enabled or if you can
support these kind of things in your
backend architecture
so how do you see customers using
rockset now
you know is it for augmenting some parts
of the stack or replacing
some services so rockset by itself
is a sql api on semi-structured data
so in general people can essentially use
it for
replacing a lot of their sql analytical
systems that they already have
but this is in theory this is not what
we see in practice
in practice what we actually see is that
people use rockset
for solving real-time analytical needs
take for example this fitness tracker
that i gave you examples about right
so they also have a very good way of
upselling products to
to their users but it has to be real
time at that right moment of time that
they can sell upsell
upsell a certain kind of product to the
user and it's very real time in nature
so they use rockset for this kind of use
case but on the other hand
because rockstar is a
sql system with jdbc api
sql apis on large data sets very quickly
we see that people
also start using it for other use cases
just because it's very easy to use
it doesn't have any operational overhead
for our users
so what they also see is that now their
application developers
can move very fast although they might
not need the
real-time data to be one second they
might be okay with
say half an hour of data latency but the
fact that it's a schema-less ingest but
the fact that
they enable application developers to
add more features to their application
without having to talk to a database
engineer
or an etl engineer or a provisioning or
capacity planning
concept they start using rockset for
different things which are again sql on
semi-structured data
but their data latency might not need to
be one second they might be okay with 10
seconds later latest they might be okay
with 15 sec
10 minutes of data latency or 15 minutes
of radio latency just because
it makes them run faster as far as the
developers in that company is concerned
so that's what we have traditionally
seen for most of our users what about
the folks building the sas applications
so do the developers building it
need to now gain some additional skills
for roxip
our focus always has been to empower
developers
application developers to leverage the
power
of all the insights or intelligence that
is
part of all the data that they're
collecting so
most of the time the application
developers who use
rockset they don't really need to have a
data team
or a data engineering team to handle all
the data needs
they typically start off with making
sql queries over rest so rockset is
essentially a sql query engine
so they dump a lot of json or csv or xml
data into rockset it could be dumped at
one time
or the application developer can also
tell rock said that oh my data is all in
s3 so please
suck it in from there or my data is in
kafka so keep continuously telling
and the thing that they have to learn is
how to make a sql query of a rest
so this is one option for most of our
application developers
we also have a python sdk and a java sdk
where if you know just python you could
use python constructs to make queries
that automatically get generated
but the even more interesting thing is
that let's say one application developer
generates some sql query and iterates
using the sql query and then finds out
that this is the real sql query to be
made
he can actually park the sql query as
something called a query lambda
so rockstar has this concept of a query
lambda which is basically
a sql query that can be stored in the
back end with obviously parameterized
sql query
and what it exposes is a rest api that
you can
hit from any machine or any browser so
you can just
hit a rest api it's not no sql on your
client side anymore the client just
hits a query lambda with a query lambda
id
and in the back end this sql query is
executed and returned back to the
application
so we have seen that many people starts
to use rockset as a developer
api because not everybody needs to know
sql
if one developer knows sql and he parks
it as a
query lambda now all other developers in
his company starts to use that query
lambda
you can actually use it from any
language you know because it's just a
rest endpoint it has no sequel
thing or it doesn't need to link in any
rocks at sdks or anything at all
so the developer adoption is pretty
minimal
the barrier to adoption is very minimal
for a new developer he doesn't have to
learn some new things that are rockstar
specific
are you tracking any technical
challenges
that you know you haven't solved yet but
you have encountered we're working with
customers
absolutely so typically customers in
different verticals have different
requirements
take for example in the healthcare
industry
there are certain rules and regulations
that are mandated
by the government like take for example
in the healthcare industry there is
something called hipaa
regulation so we are working to making
sure that rockset is
hipaa compliant but in the other hand we
have ways to be able to mask
certain fields of your data so that if
somebody has health data
and they still want to use docset today
they could mask out certain fields of
your data so that roxa doesn't get to
know about any of those let's say you
have some pii data
that that customer cannot share with
rock so they can very easily mask it
they can hash it to a certain value so
we have tools to be able to
ensure that our customers are adhering
to the
regulations that they need to similarly
say for financial
companies they might have some other
sets of
requirements that rockstar might not
meet especially related to
the security of the data essentially
right you can talk about it as shock to
compliance soc
to compliance so we are working on some
of those some of those are needed
to put more sensitive data into rockset
and
we will have all those compliances
mostly done
in another two three months or so or
maybe a month or so from now
that's one area the second area of
challenges
that as a cloud service and not just
specific to rockset but any other cloud
service
is the ability to give our developers
people who use rockstar those developers
the ability to debug
bugs in their code by themselves right
so we are building tools
and processors so that they can we can
help them debug
bugs in their code quickly and easily
that's basically one way for us to make
sure that people can
run at full speed when they're using
rock set some of these are difficult to
solve because
the variety of problems are quite big
thanks for all that
drew best so my takeaway from this
section really was the fact that
embedding into the sas apps is
really helping make the products
themselves better
in real time reacting quickly handling
much higher query volumes
many more data types and as we had
talked about earlier in the very first
section
this does introduce operational overhead
there's additional things
these as developers have to account for
to also build the workflows to react to
this
and also to match the demands yeah
that's a great summary
all these things are important all these
things have to fit in place
and complement one another to be able to
embed analytics into your application
so let's start to wrap up now i hope we
covered
uh a lot of ground and at least the key
things that you were hoping to cover
is there anything that we missed that
you would like to talk about
for real-time analytics operational
complexity is definitely something that
is top of mind for most people
not because it is hard but because
even in earlier times people could
actually do some of these real-time
analytics if they cobble together
five different software solutions and
the hire five people to be able to
do real-time analytics but this is the
real differentiator i think is that
people are seeing more and more
solutions in the market to be able to do
real-time analytics as a can solution
rockset is definitely
one of the primary ones there where you
can just point and click
and different data sources and you can
think about data as an api
rather than thinking of data as having
gravity and
like trying to do a lot of heavyweight
lifting
so if there are tools that people can
use that
that can make them use data as a real
simple api they don't have to think
about the complexities of queries or
scaling up and down or
fault tolerance or whatever else that's
a great enabler i feel for
making these embedded real-time
analytics solutions
super useful and adopted by lots of
developers
thank you how can people contact you
please go to rockset.com
so rockset is a hosted service which
means that
as a user you don't have to install
anything you go to rockset.com
click and sign up for an account and
within five minutes you'll be actually
be able to use and try connecting your
data set to rockstar and making it
making queries
sometimes if you want to know more about
the back end instead of
trying rockstar as a service you could
also just click on the demo request
or you can just send me email and we can
definitely help you answer your
questions and
see how we can help in setting up your
system so you can use it
thank you so much dubai this was a very
very interesting session for me i hope
our listeners enjoyed it and learned
from it as well
thanks a lot for coming hey thank you
thanks kanchan i really enjoyed
the discussion with you thank you this
is kanchan shrinky for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening